that's a tough question I am optimistic
that we could address the problem
I am pessimistic that we are running out
the clock needlessly on arguments that
are totally out of date and not worth
settling so I I'm I am fearful that we
will not address this but I think we
could address it and I think we now just
barely know enough to start going down
that road I don't think we know enough
to describe the end state but I do think
we know enough to embark and that we
also know enough to figure out how to
build the structure we need as we move
in the direction that we know it to be
are you talking about the environment
are you talking about just the
proliferation of human society like well
I think we've faced many potentially
existential threats and that they are
not independent of each other they are
the result of a small number of errors
in thinking that are reproduced across a
large swath of the landscape and I think
what we are lacking is not the knowledge
it's the wisdom that tells us now is the
time to move it is the time to put
certain things aside that have been very
important in the past but have lost
their significance such as the debate
between right and left is it looks
increasingly to me like it is a debate
over you know it's a VHS Betamax debate
it's a debate over something that no
longer matters and that it is
successfully preventing natural
alignment amongst those people who favor
a core set of values that if we were not
disagreeing over
these archaic questions we we would move
forward together it has become apparent
in talking to folks across the
left-right divide from me that there is
so much agreement about the desirability
of a fair society and so little
agreement over how advantageous meddling
in civilization is that we are unable to
confront the real obstacle in other
words I think if you sat people down on
the right and you said if it were true
that we could hedge out the risk of
capture and of unintended consequences
of policies that made civilization more
fair would you favor it most people on
the right would favor it and they would
say but you can't right and if you said
to the people on the left if you had to
recognize that solution making often
produces problems that you did not
anticipate could you accept that
oftentimes the things that have noble
objectives are more costly than they are
valuable they would say sure but that's
not what we're talking about
in fact there's lots of solutions that
we can just drag off the shelf and
employ them and be better off so if you
can get people to recognize that what
they're really differing over is not
what society we should want to build
most good people agree we want a society
that works that liberates people that
isn't authoritarian and onerous and
overly interested in regulating you out
of taking risks that are yours to take
people who can agree on that are really
disagreeing over how likely it is that a
particular policy proposal will bring us
closer to that objective or take us
farther away but we're not talking about
policy that has been
updated for modern circumstances we're
talking about solutions that are
antiquated and frankly just simply don't
make sense because the people who
engineered them could not possibly have
been aware of what effect the internet
would have or you know robotic
manufacturing or what the downsides of
small changes in the composition of the
atmosphere would be so we have to update
our understanding of how to make
solutions that work that is much easier
now than it was for our ancestors in
governance right and so I think you know
the most powerful idea to me is that if
you push any value to an extreme it
creates a dystopian nightmare if you
love freedom and you say well I want
everybody to be free at all times to do
anything they want you create a total
catastrophe for justice on the other
hand if you say look I know you love
freedom but you got to be adult about it
you can have 85% of the freedom that you
would get if you were totally free right
and here's what you're gonna get an
exchange you're gonna get a system that
protects you from unforeseeable medical
mishaps that is going to enhance the
ability of your children to engage
puzzles that will make the smarter as
adults you're gonna get all of these
other things and you're gonna get them
very cheaply you're gonna give up 15% of
something that you have an awful lot of
and what you're gonna get is 90% of some
other stuff that is really important to
you - you just don't realize it
people would accept that so recognizing
that there are tensions between all of
the things that we want and that an
adult is somebody who's capable of
recognizing that those tensions have an
implication for what you should actually
pursue you don't pursue any one thing
obsessively you don't even if you know
you
passionate about art and you want to
spend all your time at it you don't
pursue art to the point that you starve
to death right you take some time off
and even if our art is what you want to
do with every bit of free time you have
you don't want it to take over from
fundamental functions in your life so
governance is like this we can have most
of the things that we would all agree
are good we can't have all of any of
them but we don't need all of any of
them we can actually engineer a system
it's totally non utopian but it's very
successful at delivering outcomes that
are desirable without being the nanny
state without being onerous and
meddlesome and dictatorial I don't think
a hundred years ago that was foreseeable
I think we were stuck with partial
solutions and people became entrenched
in the idea that they were correct and
so they lost sight of what was
incomplete about them and you know I
don't want to fall into that same craft
that's always a danger and you have to
be aware of whether or not you've become
convinced of something that's really a
fiction but what I would say is I think
this is why you're hearing this from a
biologist is that biology is a totally
non utopian landscape every creature
every creature I mean down to the
tiniest bacterium is an absolute marvel
of engineering with no engineer right it
all happened because those tensions were
capable over long periods of time of
writing themselves into the code that
creates these entities and it is not
inconceivable that we humans now
understanding the rules of complexity
space can build a system that does the
same thing for us so that governance is
highly successful but not it does not
impose itself on us in ways that make us
feel constrained well it constrain us a
bit sure it has to the fact is we have
lost the ability to say
you know what I don't want to be part of
civilization I'm gonna go be a
hunter-gatherer we can't do that you're
signed up for civilization and that
means that you're signed up you can't
decide on your own that you want to
drive on the other side of the road
we're gonna regulate you into driving on
the correct side of the road and if you
demonstrate that you're not interested
in listening to us you don't get to
drive right that's natural and it's
acceptable it's a small price to pay do
you really want the freedom to drive on
whatever side of the road you feel like
on any given day or would you rather be
constrained into driving on a
predictable side of the road so that you
don't end up killing somebody or being
killed
of course you'd prefer it any reasonable
person would so there's a lot that looks
like that where if you could really see
the view from 30,000 feet you'd
understand yeah I don't love the idea of
regulation nobody does but these
regulations are more liberating than
they are constraining they actually free
you to drive and get to work rather than
you know be terrified at any moment that
somebody's gonna come careening out of
nowhere and hitch so you're an optimist
I'm a very optimistic pessimist or very
pessimistic optimist I mean you know I
don't know how to put this I I think the
thing is I'm I don't know what it means
to or what the term is for somebody who
defines themself as an optimist or a
pessimist I'm post whatever that is and
the reason that I'm most whatever
there's glass yeah well there's a
there's a unfortunately I didn't come up
with it but there's a saying I like
which is the optimist thinks the glass
is half-full the pessimist thinks the
glass is half-empty and the engineer
thinks it's too big how much do refills
costs well my question yeah
spoken like a recently starving student
so I would say I'm not I'm not an
optimist or pessimist what I am is
somebody who recognizes that there's
only one way out of this and that is we
have to figure out how to escape the
dysfunctional conversation that is
preventing us from fixing our system and
find our way to a system that at least
knows how to
itself and until we either fail at that
or succeed at it there's no point in
investing in anything else you brought
up this term of maturity or acting like
an adult is that a heuristic and is
there such a thing as in the natural
world or in the animal kingdom of
maturity that the human need human
beings need to grasp and develop in
themselves well that's a really
interesting question I mean I would say
you certainly see if you were to survey
animals of some type all right let's say
we looked at Jaguars if you were to
survey Jaguars you would surely find
that the oldest individuals actually
invested their efforts in a way that was
sensitive to subtleties in the
environment that matter and insensitive
to things that were a distraction right
and that happens for two reasons one
Jaguar is a smart animal and they they
learn over time so the older you are the
more experience you've had in this wiser
you get the other reason is because
those Jaguars that aren't very good at
behaving in a wise way are eliminated
over time so the ones that are left
after a large number of years tend to be
the ones that got it right in the first
place so our older Jaguars wise
undoubtedly undoubtedly they're wise
about the stuff of Jaguar existence in a
way that young cars are probably foolish
so wisdom does have analogs I mean maybe
it's not even analogs it's just real
real wisdom but then I guess there's a
question - about structures and actually
this is going to be yeah it's it's a
fractal you will surely find that the
oldest claves of organisms have a design
that anticipates changes in the
environment
they're greater so in other words when
we look at what our I think
the term has a certain resonance to it
but I think it has the wrong emphasis we
call certain things living fossils right
so if we look at dragons lives for
example or sharks these are designs that
have existed for a very long period of
time and the versions that we see today
are modern versions but they're less
modified from that original design than
something like a fly you know or a trout
so what can we say about those designs
you know the term living fossil tends to
suggest that there's something not very
up-to-date about them when really the
answer is they got it right so early
that the design has remained largely
unchanged because they can compete even
with that design so if you look at a
dragonfly for example it has four large
wings if you compare it to a fly two of
those wings have been reduced to control
structures called Hall tiers you know it
sort of seems like the dragonfly is
missing those special control structures
that allow flies to do certain things on
the other hand you've ever watched a
dragonfly do what it does that's an
amazingly acrobatic creature and the
only reason that it exists in the
present is that that ancient design is
totally capable of keeping up in at
least some environments in modern
circumstances so I would argue that
although there's no intelligence to it
that there is wisdom in those older
designs that have persisted without as
much change and that sometimes these
younger designs seem great but then some
change in the environment will reveal
that actually it wasn't - it wasn't
wisdom it was it was like youthful
exuberance about something that then
loses its appeal when the climate
changes and that design no longer
functions the tensions that give rise to
wise designs that's found in the
biological landscape can we use the
checks and balances inherent in that
tensive system to refine government kind
of by the leeward to submit
to certain pressures that propel it
towards more and more wise
functionalities that's exactly that's
exactly it and that is exactly why you
find me focused on the group of topics
that I'm focused on so I started out
studying trade-offs and I started out
studying them for my own reasons because
they actually just simply were the key
to cracking the puzzles that I found
entertaining but once I began to reverse
engineer what the rules of trade-offs
were and these were rules that you can't
look up we don't they're not things that
people are well enough versed in that
there's some place you can go and say
well what are the rules about how
trade-offs work so that's what I worked
on for my dissertation and those rules
it turns out have nothing to do with
biology they have to do with complex
systems in which there is an objective
any complex system with an objective has
to abide by these rules and knowing that
means that actually you're in a position
to infer from dragonflies spruce trees
whatever it may be you're able to infer
what these tensions must look like and
how a wise individual or a process that
weeds out unwise designs and preserves
the wise designs you can figure out
exactly what that would look like and
you can map it on to government's it's
really a perfectly natural thing to do
you can also map it on to engineering
space we can look at you know for
example the design of aircraft and you
can use the very same rules that govern
you know a plant you know it's more
obvious when you're talking about
something that flies but you can take
the rules of trade off land and you can
abstract them from plants and you can
apply them to aircraft or governance or
markets you can do it in those
circumstances and the amazing thing is
it doesn't take a whole heck of a lot of
retool the real work is just figuring
out how the mapping goes right so you
know it's very tempting for you
to imagine that corporations are like
creatures they're not that's not the
right mapping and so if you try to map
the creature rules onto corporations it
won't work for various reasons including
the fact that corporations don't die
right and so their uncreate like in this
way but there is a proper mapping and if
you can find it the rules are quite
intuitive in fact and the ability if
people were more aware of what the
implications that these rules were we
could take a lot of people who are
trapped in one version of utopianism or
another and we can say here's why
utopianism will never work it's not that
your idea isn't quite right or it is
your idea can't possibly be right right
to the extent that it is utopium it
violates a rule of nature that doesn't
yet have a name I'm still wrestling with
what you mean by utopia is it because
it's a closed system in some way and
nature won't abide by something that
that's perfect and in a certain sort of
closed simplistic fashion no I mean
there may be elements of that but first
of all what I mean by utopian is two
things utopians tend to focus on a
single value that they wish to see
maximized right and whether that value
is freedom or justice or free love yeah
whatever it is anything that maximizes
one value is a catastrophe because of
its massive cost in every other value
and
so the other thing that utopians do is
they tend to imagine that they know what
the system needs to be structured like
in order to reach their one value right
and they so they ignore the collateral
damage of the other values they assume
that those will be prettied up later or
something it's impossible actually and
they assume that they know what
structure creates the elevation in this
value and they are always under
imaginative in the the unintended
consequences so what I would say is
effectively utopians are searching for
perpetual motion machines and they don't
realize that justice with perpetual
motion there's a law of nature that says
no such thinking can exist and as soon
as you know that no such thing can exist
then the question is alright step down
from searching for that thing there's no
obstacle to an incredibly efficient
machine there's an obstacle to be
perfectly efficiently seen right so as
soon as you recognize that you shouldn't
be searching for a perfectly efficient
machine then you can start searching for
a marvelously efficient train and so
that's really what I'm arguing is that
the state of governance which we cannot
describe from here but that we should be
pursuing is marvelously efficient
marvelously effective and minimally
invasive that it can be all of those
things but as soon as you say I don't
want an invasive at all well you're
screwed it's going to be somewhat
invasive if you say I wanted to be
perfectly efficient no you're done it
can't be perfectly efficient it can be
marvelously efficient so this is this is
the maturity recognizing that not only
are there trade-offs in the world but
that they are absolutely 100% guaranteed
to apply to the thing that you value
most right that that thing that you
value most has a cost in terms of
everything else and the more of it you
want the higher the cost in every other
thing you care about once you realize
that then the question isn't how do I
get
all of that one thing it's well how do I
get most of that one thing and get
enough of everything else in order that
I can make a life out of it and it's
just not that hard a problem once you
spot the the the sirens song of
perfection
I think you need to be careful in one
regard I don't want to say you can judge
the system based on the economic
well-being let's say of the students it
produces because first of all students
in one generation don't face the same
market that students in another
generation you see you certainly can't
compare between generations that way the
other thing that's true is that economic
well-being is not the only kind of
well-being I would say that an education
that does not leave students in a
position to manage their lives is a
failure but that students some students
will choose to prioritize other things
over getting rich and there's nothing
wrong with that it may well be healthy
and in fact most of the members of the
Academy are choosing to be part of a
system in which getting rich is almost
impossible and so it's not surprising in
some sense that the values that are
alternative to those that the market
pays for have been highly esteemed
within the Academy on the other hand to
the extent that the Academy is producing
people who are talking utter nonsense
and imagining that it is sophisticated
and enlightened that system is a failure
now I don't think that we can say that
the entire educational apparatus is a
failure but we can say that the part of
the apparatus that is a failure is
taking over more and more territory the
number of classes in a university that
are immune to this extremely broken way
of thinking is ever smaller and I think
we can even see from here the day in
which it will be no classes that are
immune because every class is going to
be subject to some set of rules that is
built around this very naive notion of
privilege and white supremacy and all of
that so that day is coming and the
sooner those who are hired will be hired
based on their willingness to to go
along with that program
it's absolutely part of the program and
if there's one thing that people fail to
appreciate about the social justice
movement where it interfaces with the
Academy is that just because what is
being said is crazy to the point of
absurdity does not mean that the
strategic plan is absurd the strategic
plan is far more effective than you
would expect based on the sophistication
of the ideas that are being promulgated
so in a certain way the system itself is
pretty strong robust and anti fragile
even if the ideology inside of it is
broken corrupt and the insurgency yeah
yes the insurgency is far more effective
than you would expect it to be based on
how correct the things that it claims
are true actually are how it is that
disconnect happen that that belief the
belief the beliefs themselves are
incoherent and destructive but the
system which houses the beliefs is
incredibly efficient I suspect that the
answer is weirdly evolutionary so
Heather and I encountered the postmodern
stuff in 1992 at the University of
California Santa Cruz
we took an anthropology class that
described itself as about human
evolution and it turned out to be a
postmodern take on evolution those ideas
have been morphing and bubbling through
a quadrant of the university system
since that point and of course a bit
before each cohort that has encountered
them has wheeled them in some
circumstances and those arguments that
were hard to defeat its persistent and
those arguments that were easy to defeat
have perished which means that the new
crop of student shows up and they're
handed this toolkit of
arguments that are incredibly hard to
confront right not because they're true
but because the way they're structured
they are built you know each of these
definitions is can't be pinned down you
can't figure out what they mean by
equity on the other hand if you start
asking questions about equity you're
gonna run afoul of a booby-trap that's
gonna have you portrayed as a white
supremacist so that is a very potent
combination really a text it's brilliant
but it isn't brilliant on the basis that
those who are wielding it are brilliant
it's brilliant on the basis that
selection has weeded out those parts
that didn't work so I think that's what
we're up against and it's very
frustrating but I would I would argue it
is a mistake just because the movement
looks so full of foolishness to dismiss
the structure as foolish it's really
much stronger than and you would have
more even wise in a certain way it's
wise in the way that a dragonfly is wise
you